"Chrono Trigger" is sometimes considered
the best RPG ever made.
But, is it really an RPG?
After studying the subject for a DECADE,
I have actually realized that...
Yes. Yes it is...
Not the result I wanted.
(as the viewer)
"Kilian, two videos ago you said all Japanese games
are bad, but here you are, praising Chrono Trigger.
You can't just stop being cinephobic."
Okay, let me explain.
"Chrono Trigger" was conceived by Akira Toriyama,
creator of "Dragon Ball Z: Abridged",
Yuji Horii, creator of, uh... "Chrono Trigger", and
Sakaguchi, creator of millions of weeaboos.
They came up with the idea while studying
computer graphics in the United States.
That means that Chrono Trigger was born on U.S. soil.
That makes it an American citizen.
They developed this 15-hour-long
game that feels like 40 hours.
Usually that's considered a bad thing, but here it's... not considered a good thing... but it's considered a thing.
The game starts with the main character,
Chrono Trigger, waking up.
You know he is the protagonist,
because he has spiky red hair.
There is a fair in town to celebrate the year 1000, but
they celebrate the new year... in summertime?!
Silly fantasy countries.
At the fair, Chrono runs into this girl named Marle,
then, she decides to spend time with Chrono,
which tells us that Chrono is attractive.
Then they do normal fair stuff,
like fighting robots.
Lucca, Chrono's best friend, has invented a
teleportation device. Marle decides to try it out.
But the machine reacts to the metal necklace,
and sends her back in time.
That's why when you are at the airport, they ask
you to take off all your metals before you
go through those... "Terrorist Scanners".
Too much iron, and you can end up in ancient Rome.
Chrono goes after her and travels back
four hundred years... but because the planet
has moved quite a lot since then...
he ends up in a vacuum and dies.
Fortunately, there is a guy in the Middle Ages who
looks exactly like him, and no-one will know,
because he is a silent protagonist.
So, Marle was actually the Princess, Nadia,
and when she ended up here, everyone mistook
her for a kidnapped Queen.
Even though she is like ten years younger.
Let's be honest here. The King knows.
The King doesn't care.
But, because they stopped searching for the real Queen,
she dies, and Marle disappears.
Kinda like that movie from the 80's,
starring Michael--
Nope. Not doing it.
We go to the Church and meet Frog.
No-one cares he's a frog.
People probably didn't even notice,
they were pretty ugly back in the Middle Ages.
I mean, wh-what am I looking at here?
Is that even a human?
The Queen was kidnapped by a yellow mole.
Yay~ we did it! The queen is back, Marle is back,
and by now you probably want me to explain how
Chrono supposedly died,
but what about all the other people?
But I'm not gonna do that, because
I wrote myself into a corner.
Back in the year 1000, Crono is arrested for kidnapping the Princess, and dragged to court.
(as the Chancellor)
"Your honor, we believe Mr. Trigger kidnapped her
to cut off her ears, and create a necklace."
"We don't have any proof, other than the fact that he picked up her necklace before he picked up her."
Everyone agrees, and Crono is now in jail.
But right before he gets to end his miserable existence...
he gets saved by Lucca, who has finally snapped,
and is going on a killing spree, but is using this
rescue as an excuse.
They kill a bunch of underpaid government
workers, and a robot dragon.
Then, they actually kidnap the Princess,
and travel to the future.
You idiot. If you are escaping from someone,
travel to the PAST. Now, all they have to do is wait.
Welcome to 2300. The future is pretty bad, but they have, what, 1300 years of new and fresh and funny maymays.
But, instead of checking that out, they decide
they want to go back.
Eventually, they find this computer that tells us
where we are supposed to go,
and what destroyed the world.
In the year 1999, a giant monster
came from underground.
Wrong again, scientists!
We know the monster is evil. Not only did it destroy
civilization, but it couldn't wait one more year.
To get to the new portal, you have to race.
But I intentionally lost, because I was uncomfortable
destroying a guy in a wheelchair...
and he calls me worthless!
Okay then.
Play with fire, you get ICED.
The way to the portal is blocked, so we resurrect this robot...
and then THESE robots beat him up.
I don't want to get involved.
He did it~! We go through the portal and
end up... in the "End of Time"?
This senior citizen tells you that only three
people can travel through a portal.
I was wondering how that works, is it mass?
Because the robot can cover three people,
and this place, how did it get all of this stuff?
But also Oxygen, Gravity, Vitamin D...
and then I watched "The Martian"...
and it all made sense.
That's not a man! That's a cactus.
In the Middle Ages, everyone was dying of the plague,
corpses rotting on the streets,
but that place is better than this one,
so... we go there.
The humans are at war with Magus, which is a wizard named Magnus, but he has severe dyslexia,
and he created Lavos.
His troops have taken over a bridge.
Ozzie, Magus's second-in-command,
summons a giant skeleton.
Then... why even use the small skeletons?
We also find out that a "legendary hero" has
appeared, and this has caused Frog to go
into a clinical depression.
To be the hero, you need a necklace,
and a legendary sword.
We fight a fat, yet ripped guy, to get the broken sword,
and we steal the necklace from the
actual Legendary Hero.
You're becoming a surgeon, and you're liking it.
On the blade, it says "Melchior".
That's a swordsmith who lives 400 years later.
What a mystery!
Or, it's just a very common name.
But he tells you that to repair the sword, he
needs a red crystal that doesn't exist anymore.
So, we go back to pre-history.
In 65,000,000 B.C., humans are fighting the Reptilians,
because the humans are cool and reptiles are NERDS.
The only thing these cavemen care about is Smirnoff,
so they immediately throw a party.
When the chief is absolutely shitfaced,
she gives Crono the red crystal.
This could be illegal, but these idiots haven't
invented a court system yet.
Then, they fight a ripped dinosaur.
Lots of ripped creatures in this game.
This was the original concept art for Lavos.
The sword gets Frog out of his depression.
Wrong again, psychologists!
We see this flashback, where we find out that
Frog is actually a guy named Glenn.
Really?
Magus killed his best friend, and turned
him into a frog...
but he got a free necklace, so it was not all bad.
The sword cuts open a mountain.
That wasn't advertised.
Then, they enter the castle, and fight
this guy, and
this guy.
I died here, forgot to save,
ended up back here and developed Alcoholism.
Why does Ozzie just stand there?
But he escapes, and we are ready to fight Magus
and stop him from creating Lavos.
(as Magus)
"Guys, I did not create Lavos. How much
spare time do you think I have?"
"I am going to fight him, so calm down. Just
going to summon a little bit of Lavos."
But his dyslexia causes him to misread the spell,
and they are sent back in time.
The gang wakes up in the Stone Age, and they tell us
a couple of their friends have been kidnapped.
Lucca suggests genocide. So that's what we do.
But when everyone is extinct,
Lavos comes down from space, and destroys
the reptiles' lair, so it was all for nothing.
Hey, another portal! Could lead anywhere...
but risks are fun!
Oh... we've fucked up.
Welcome to 12,000 B.C. and the Kingdom of Zeal.
It's a kingdom for magic users.
People who are not magic users live in a cave.
Just because you can't use magic doesn't
mean you shouldn't take a bath.
Zeal's greatest achievement is that the world uses their exact currency for over 14,000 years.
Also, no inflation!
But, they also have a machine that drains Lavos' energy.
But they have yet to invent security, so
Crono visits the Queen's Meeting.
But they get captured!
The Princess rescues them, and says,
"Rescue the 'Guru of Light', who is trapped on the..."
It's called that, because that's where they send
people who make inappropriate comments.
But a man called "The Prophet" shows up,
and throws us back into the portal.
So, they decide to take a vacation to the future.
And there, they find a time machine.
The gang goes back and climbs the Mountain of Woe, and sets the Guru free.
It's the swordsmith! Or someone who looks exactly
like him and shares his name.
Statistically, it's very possible.
He gives us a knife that can
destroy the Lavos Machine.
Currently the machine is in a palace in the ocean.
We need to teleport there, because the developers
have not programmed swimming.
In our way is the Zeal General, Dalton,
who is working as security.
Oh my God, we've changed history!
We enter the palace and get to the machine,
then we stick the knife in it.
Yeaaaaah!!
And then the knife makes the machine even stronger.
You traitor!! You've doomed us all!!
Lavos is awakened... and I defeat him.
So I had to reload the game, because
you're not supposed to...
When the party is dead, The Prophet
reveals himself to be Magus,
and then he gets his ass kicked.
Then Crono sacrifices himself... and... dies...
So... he's dead...
Then Lavos goes back to sleep again, because he
did the "five more minutes" thing.
The Princess teleports them out of there,
and then they wake up in the village,
and the Ocean Palace is flying now!
But we get kidnapped by Dalton,
and there's another prison escape!
All good games have at least two prison escapes.
Dalton puts wings on the time machine.
What is fascinating about this scene is tha--
WAIT. "We have lift-off, Houston!"???
I have so many questions...
They fight Dalton on the time machine.
Good thing they are JRPG characters, so
they don't fall off.
Airship crashes.
Then, we go up this cape, because there's
nothing else to do.
Here, we meet a familiar face.
(as Magus)
"Okay, froggy, maybe you are angry about
the killing of your best friend and all that.
But I know how to save Crono,
so I guess that makes us... besties??"
We speak to the guy that built the time machine that
we stole. He says, "Climb a mountain", and that
they need a doll that looks exactly like Crono.
It can be bought from Norstein Bekkler,
in 1000 A.D., for 30,000 MONEY.
They climb the mountain and go
back to this exact moment,
and switch out Crono with the doll.
Wait, why did we even need to replace him with the doll?
Oh, they scammed me.
There are lots of great sidequests
before the final showdown.
There is one quest where you leave the robot in
the desert for 400 years,
and then he dies. Maybe he can be repaired, but the desert thing is not covered by the warranty.
We also get to see Lucca watch her
mother lose her legs,
another side mission is where Frog finds out why everyone in the Middle Ages have cool names,
like "Magus", "Cyrus", "Slash"... and he is
stuck with the name Glenn.
My favorite side mission is the one
where Crono travels back to
the 50's and meets up with Doc Brown.
Damn it! Almost made it through the entire video.
There are TWENTY endings to Chrono Trigger,
depending on when you fight Lavos.
The hardest way to beat him is...
to engage him in an intelligent discussion,
because he has had 65 million years to think.
You can fly the time machine into his shell and break it...
I don't believe that for a second.
Lavos destroyed his own shell, to
support the defense industry!
If you don't fight him at all, he will eventually
come to you and ask "What's up?"
In the normal ending, you enter the Flying Palace
and confront the Queen of Zeal.
(as Queen Zeal)
"No, I'm not gonna fight you. I'm a Queen,
not a Warrior! Fight the Lavos Machine!"
(Battle Theme)
"Oh... right... that's an inanimate object.
Fine, I'm summoning Lavos..."
Here we are... the Final Showdown...
First part, Lavos transforms into previous bosses.
You idiot. Don't use attack patterns we already know!
Then, his head explodes and we enter.
( ͡° ͜ʖ ͡°)
Oh shit! Lavos is actually Cell!
Then that form dies, and...
Oh shit, there's a third form...
Oh, that's it?
Huh.
Then, they celebrate. Yay~
Everyone returns to their times and it's very sad.
Final Thought: Every game made before the original
Xbox is bad... but Chrono Trigger is less bad,
And that is the Kilian Experience.
Hi there! Thanks for one million views on the previous video! I now have a Steam group, and a subreddit.
Yay~
In the next recap, I am doing a shorter game.
Yes, Chrono Trigger is only fifteen hours, but they
managed to cram forty hours into those fifteen.